Abram Tromka Papers
Abram Tromka Papers
1934-1961
Tromka, Abram, 1896-1954.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the Polish-born American Jewish painter, etcher, serigrapher. Also worked under name Abraham Phillips. Collection includes correspondence, exhibition catalogs, photographs of Tromka and his work, published material, including articles and clippings about Tromka.
148707
Biographical History
Abram Tromka (1896-1954) was a Polish-born American Jewish painter, etcher and serigrapher. He also worked under the name Abraham Phillips.
Born in Poland, Tromka came to the United States at the age of 11 and attended public school in New York City. Although he studied at an early age with Henri and Bellows, Tromka was for the most part self-taught; he worked mostly in oil, gouache, watercolor, serigraphy, drawing and etching. As a youth, he illustrated the book The House on Henry Street by Lillian D. Wald, and his etching entitled "The sweet potato vendor was purchased by the Metropolitan Museum of Art when he was only nineteen.
Tromka's work has been exhibited in museums in the United States and in Central and South America, and is in the permanent collections of several important museums, including the Biro Bidjan Museum in the former Soviet Union.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Abram Tromka Papers consists of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts (both of Tromka and of others) and published material (clippings, press releases, exhibition catalogs).
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically; outgoing is arranged chronologically. The remaining series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973.; Tromka, Ann.; Tromka, Abram, 1896-1954.; House on Henry Street.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Etchers -- United States.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Polish Americans.; Serigraphers -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Artists.; Etchers.; Painters.; Serigraphers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ann Tromka, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A - N, miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Brooklyn Museum, 1934; 1945,; 1946,; 1952 (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Institute, 1941; 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Ellis, Havelock, undated (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Of others
    - Tromka, Ann, 1961 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Art and artists (Box 1)
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Tromka (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Tromka's work (Box 1)
  - Recipes (Box 1)
  - USSR (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Of Tromka
    - Drawing (Box 1)
    - Journal of southern trip (Box 1)
    - Sketchbook (Box 1)
  - Of others
    - "Abram Tromka" / Dr. Isaac Klcomok (Box 1)
    - "Foreword to catalogue for Tromka exhibition" / Herman Baron, 1956 (Box 1)
    - "Foreword for Catalogue" / Philip Evergood, 1961 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Articles about Tromka (Box 1)
  - Book, The House on Henry Street by L. Wald, illustrated by A. Phillips (Tromka) (Box 1)
  - Exhibitions, one-man shows (Box 1)
  - Exhibitions, with others (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings about Tromka (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings by Tromka (Box 2)
  - Press releases (Box 2)
  - Reproductions of Tromka's work (Box 2)